go to copy or not to copy that is the
question from chimpanzees to the
foundation of human technological
culture recently appeared in physics of
Life reviews
let me see if this works yeah sorry
so it always start with a jigsaw puzzle
and and the Apostle is why I highly
Innovative species like Jim Banks is do
not live in a complex technological
world so we know chimpanzees are very
inventive they are very creative they
are insightful they can learn socially
but what we don't see in the same extent
or similar extent we're seeing humans is
the accumulation of complexity across
Generations so you can see here in these
images we have one of the more complex
and demanding tasks that chimpanzees
perform cracking nuts open and they can
combine different tools they can use it
in the appropriate order so this means
they are very insightful and yet
if we compare with a rocket that can
bring civilization to Mars
um it is clear that accumulation of
Technology across generation works very
different in humans and other non-human
species
so the the basic question or the one
million dollars question is why does
innovation fail to translate into
technological cumulative complexity in
chimpanzees
does it all to a limited capacity to
copy with Fidelity or what we is
referred as three imitation which means
reproducing not only the end result that
will be emulating or emulation but also
the steps that lead to that end result
so according to this view failure to
copy Innovation with faithful accuracy
hampers the intra and intergenerational
spread and any ensuing ratcheting up
effects so possibly when coping with
Fidelity is impeded Innovative
performances are unlikely to leave their
protagonists and this brings us back to
the discussion we had the other day in
the snakes and others paper where we
said that
after 2 million years ago eliomo
produced this almond shame be facility
flaked stones and but this um kind of
artifacts that we we don't even dare to
call them tools were not copied by con
specific log servers because perhaps
they were not attributing to them any
kind of functional use so perhaps they
were not seen as a tools and where the
result of manual inactions so
so to write it up complexity it is
important that inventions that these
tools are copied with sufficient
Fidelity so that they retain the
fundamental features or attributes that
make them functional
so following the steps of demonstrated
tool manufacture by an expert model to
the letter is the simplest fastest and
cheapest way to make sure that copies of
the original artifact are accurate I've
here cheapest we refer to in terms of
expenditure of energy
so if the copies are functional hence
useful they keep circulating in the
group Community longer and these skills
increase the opportunities for one or
more individuals different from the
original inventor to add in complexity
so for example one individual inventable
and spur and 100 years later the
simultaneous Copa is discovered
and another individual adds to it to
this super a sharp coca point and so on
so here is an interesting concept of
Ratchet effect that would explain in
part why humans have built such complex
cultural and technological work so the
idea of the ratchet effect is that no
generation starts from scratch instead
inventions and cultural products created
by one generation are kept in mind and
transmitted to the Next Generation this
way every generation is better off
supposedly than the one that preceded it
so here we can think of books books that
are wonderful way of keeping information
sharing it across generations and among
the same generation also
so does technological complexity and
success in humans is not dependent
solely on the geneality of one or few
individuals it is a joint and devil
where many individuals contributed
specific expertise and skills to produce
increasingly complex artifacts and again
we can think in
establishing a colony in Mars no single
human alive could achieve that alone or
we have the required expertise to
achieve that alone but all together we
can perhaps manage that so we need this
kind of shirt and knowledge and
accumulating the generation of course
so why it is some Behavior or innovation
or copies or not can be explained at the
level of social dynamics but also uh at
the level of the brain or giving a more
mechanistic explanation so explanation
why copinoist behavior in chimpses does
not occur with frequency have been often
kept at the level of social dynamics
where factors at the social Prestige
dominance
Etc said to be key to explaining whether
or not an invasion is adopted by
Observers
and these are program against the brain
to a subsidiary role here Michael and I
will be attending to identify what the
minimum cognitive requirements are that
can give rise to Innovations and their
horizontal and vertical transmission
and we also attempted to differentiate
the cognitive ingredient necessary for
Innovation from those that need to be in
place for the adoption of an innovation
so we wanted to establish a clear
developation between the brains of the
the ones that innovate and the brains of
those who observe an innovation because
we think this is important to be
analyzed separately
so in order to see which are the
mechanisms
at the level of the brain that would
allow for one Innovation to be copied we
invoked the lens of the free energy
principle
according to active inference under the
free energy principle it is through
there being limited to a restrictive
number of states that is the attracting
set that organisms minimize the
variational free energy of the internal
State and resist entropic dissipation
minimizing variation of free energy
reduces prediction sensation the
discrepancies
prediction errors that can be corrected
by active sampling of predicted sensory
inputs and perceptive modification of
predictions this is sometimes expressed
in terms of perceptual inference that is
changing predictions too much Sensations
and active inference reactively changing
Sensations to match predictions
so
innovation in a way might represent a
potential misfirings from other winning
perspective so minimizing variational
free energy can be achieved through
action same thing creatures can act
active inference in order to fulfill
their predictions and thereby reduce
discrepancy between the latter and
Sample reality
the number of states what we could refer
to as the attracting set is therefore
synonymous with minimizing variation of
energy and hence maximizing adaptive
Fitness
here Innovation represent an anomaly and
innovators are an orthodox actors or
protagonists who entertain new courses
of action or plants
new phenotypical responses that have not
been previously entertained
and according to this interpretation of
the free energy principle it is at the
level of policy selection where
innovators stand apart from the crowd
their policy selection is in a sense
faulty insofar as their ensuring
behavioral outcomes are in more contrast
to those of their fellow actors who
deploy orthod of responses that reduce
discrepancies between predictions and
Sensations thereby reducing the
prediction error and here we will talk
about Miss firing we don't do it in a
kind of negative sense it's just to
express that this new behavior these
Innovations necessarily will produce
more surprise
with this phrase I I'm kind of
paraphrasing Andy Clark in a paper in
behavioral and brain Sciences he
referred to seeing surprising things to
being able to lend credibility to the
sensory information that is not in
accordance to Prior feelings
so the family electorality density is
entertained by an individual is
restricted to the systems the brains
prior bias and beliefs equivalent
roughly speaking to its phenotypical
repertoire
this means by definition that Innovative
behaviors both unlikely to be events in
any given phenotype and crucially
difficult to recognize when observed by
Nava
shoot an Innovative behavior diverts
markedly from the reperto plausible
policies used usually by an observer
to predict another Behavior it may be
beyond the capacity of the latter
generative model to recognize it that is
to make sense of it
so large discrepancing systems are
threat to the brain because one updating
involves making energetic demands and
two risk reducing adaptive Fitness by
inappropriately changing changing the
generative models and here we need to
think that the generative model has been
selected also in a specific econation so
changing it my my half risked okay
foreign so what is required for a brain
to entertain generality models that
involve unusual or visual behaviors
the hierarchical predictive
interpretation of the brain or
hierarchically mechanistic mind an
infinite inference machine sorry implies
that each level of the hierarchy of
cerebral neuronal circuits conveys
predictions or conditional expectations
that suppress errors at the level below
while concurrently conveying errors that
permit the revision of the expectations
at the level above
plausibly dynamical Precision weighting
enables the system that is the brain to
readjust the confidence afforded to top
down expectations as opposed to
bottom-up prediction errors
in other words in order to entertain a
priority at an unlikely hypothesis it
might explain best some Behavior
witnessed it is first necessary to relax
the Precision or commitment to Prior
beliefs thus enabling new or implausible
hypothesis to explain novel Behavior
and here I introduce
some things we discussed the other day
Professor friston talk of attenuation of
sensory information in relation to
circades which is kind of switching of
this sensory information we are being
aware of and that will be the opposite
as being impressionable so
I'm quoting Professor friston here
if I can copy that means I am
impressionable I will accumulate new
evidence very quickly I have the
capacity to assign great evidence or
Precision to sensory evidence and
suspend the Precision to my prior
beliefs
this is something he he mentioned in the
last active infant recording 53.1.1
and to end this introduction
one Constable introduced in our paper
which is Central to our discussion is
that of sounds abundant surprise
So This Is A New Concept introduced to
refer to the level of mismatch between
prior beliefs or top-down predictions
and sensory information that a species
can tolerate
so first and foremost the focus of the
zbs concept is on The Observers and
their ability to make sense of
unobserved innovation
encoding and subsequent copying of an
innovation depends on the degree of
disparity or surprisal between
predictable behaviors namely those
typical of the species and the
perceptual incoming information about
novel behaviors if the set BS is white
it means that the species can give
credit to the information received
through its sentences that challenges
the prior beliefs in short a species can
register encode and potentially
reproduce Innovative behavior of serving
code specifics that deviate markedly
from customary prototypical behaviors
this species is highly impressionable if
we use the words that Professor friston
use the other day so if the serbius is
not of then a species ability to change
prior beliefs to accommodate new
evidence regarding Innovative practices
of serving on specifics is compromised
foreign
have nothing to do with the zone of
Latin solutions by tenure I'll be we are
discussing similar topics so the son of
Latin Solutions
that was introduced by tenure Kai and
Thomas refers to solutions to a problem
for instance extractive foraging that
can be achieved by an individual in
isolation during his her lifetime and
hence is not likely to be the product of
commodative culture involving social
learning when observed in the wild
and for those readers interested in this
concept they can go to the original
paper I'm I'm
showing here and also there is a
Christian paper by Andrew whiten who is
Professor in
um in San Andreas
that discusses this concept and that has
replication by other authors so it might
be a good update for those interested
also and with that I finished this short
presentation and we can enter discussion
let me stop sharing the screen I think
okay now
thank you Hector
I will bring up the notes again and to
Michael Carl or Dean whoever would like
to provide a First Response please
well I don't really have a great deal
more to add
um I think
hello
yes please continue
what's happened here
you're all good Michael we're here
Michael hello
can you hear me yes we hear you continue
yes we can I'm not quite sure what's
happened here we seem to have snakes and
ladders up on the up on the screen
um as I said I I don't think I can add
much water what Hector has just said
I think it makes a very succinct
summary of a bar paper and uh
um I would like to
certainly congratulate Hector for making
what seems to me are in a very original
and perceptive of uh observation that it
is The Observers whom we have to thank
for
uh
the copying and therefore for the
handing down of technological
achievements by early humans
[Music]
whereas too often the emphasis is being
made on the person responsible for
making a technological innovation uh but
of course unless somebody accomplish
that or at least unless it registers in
the mind of somebody else it is unlikely
ever to get copied and although this
seems to be a fairly a fairly obvious
observation it seems to have escaped
most of those who have published on the
matter is a tool and I think this is a
very original contribution on Hector's
part which deserves uh to be
complemented and uh
really that's all I wish to say I think
I'd like to throw this open to other
people and if I can illuminate or
elucidate any matters
um I'm happy to do so but I think this
is really very much uh to put it magic
Hector's brainchild and uh
congratulations
thanks Michael you're very kind but this
is our child so and you you know a lot
you have a lot to contribute so I mean I
can only learn so but thank you anyway
awesome
Coral or Dean
go ahead Carl
oh right
so I just wanted to um reiterate
Michael's admiration for both the idea
but also the very fluent
um and clear articulation of it
I was um
it was nice for me to see that
presented so succinctly because the
clarity of the ideas really um is really
very evident
um it struck me there is sort of two
um
still themes that we could discuss which
is the
um the emergence of more complicated
solutions to accurately engaging with
and modeling our world I think that was
a sort of generic theme in the first
part of the presentation but then very
quickly moved to this kernel idea this
core idea
um that it the dissemination and the
transgenerational propagation
that um can be read as some kind of
um cultural Niche Construction in a sort
of Evo Devo context depends upon being
able to recognize a particular behavior
and thereby copy and imitate I think
that that's um that was the key thing
and for me
um
just understanding the mechanics of that
from the point of view of
um belief updating and active influence
um was a I think a really useful thing
and as Hector beautifully articulated
the ability to recognize something new
and update one's generative model or
posterior beliefs depends very
sensitively on the confidence or the
Precision that you've ascribe the sense
of evidence in relation to the
precisions with which you hold your your
pride beliefs and I think that that's
absolutely crucial and I I sort of
um
highlight that issue because it is
exactly the same issue that you will
find when applying active inference in
the free energy principle to
um Psychiatry and the different ways in
which we can uh I can't remember Hector
what was your word misfire in neither a
good nor of bad sense but certainly
there are certain psychiatric
syndromes that could be regarded as
misfiring and of course is a very close
association with Innovation and
creativity and manic depressive
psychosis as you know uh you know famed
in terms of various historical figures
in uh in the Arts
um
and that I think is you know again
brings us back to this sort of key
notion of getting that balance
the balance of the Precision of our
prior constructs what we have accrued
through experienced dependent learning
and the Precision afforded evidence that
this is how the world is actually
working and how I am actually working
getting that balance right
um and that's a really difficult job and
sometimes in in computational Psychiatry
we um we try to explain this in terms of
a statistician
um in order to get the balance right you
have to be able to estimate these
precisions and this exactly the same
spirit that a statistician when making
an inference doing a t-test has to
estimate not just the difference in the
group means but also the standard error
and it's often much more difficult to
estimate the standard error
than it is to estimate the difference in
in the group means and that's standard
error is the inverse Precision it's the
weight that you afford
the meaning the significance of some
quantitative difference say a prediction
error
um so you see this theme that you know
there are two parts to inference the
first order part is just the prediction
error or the surprise but then you have
to assign our newsworthy is that you
have to actually modulate that with its
Precision so you kind of multiply by the
Precision or divide by the standard
error to get the actual thing that
matters that's going to change your mind
um and there are the whole literature on
um different kinds of people in the
context of neurodiversity that I have an
impairment in being able or possibly
have an impairment in being able to
estimate that precision and I'm thinking
here are the the poster child of this
kind of formulation which is autism
um and the idea being that there is an
early developmental failure to attenuate
sensory Precision so they are rarely
um and continually during their early
development severe people with severe
autism
um unable to ignore any of their
Sensations
um and as a consequence everything is
surprising everything's arousing
everything is in danger of revising any
beliefs very very quickly so they're
highly impressionable to the extent they
can't build
deeply coherent models of their lived
world or indeed the other artifacts such
as mum that constitutes their world so I
I'm just wondering whether you know a
species
that
um as the same kind of latitude in terms
of either biasing attention or Precision
the sensory evidence versus accumulated
prior beliefs would display the same
kind of misfiring so you can go from one
end an autistic species will be overly
impressionable it'll be too evolvable it
won't be able to remember anything from
generation to generation the converse is
a
um somebody who you you you could
imagine from a psychiatric perspective
um has committed unduly to very precise
beliefs about the world the world works
and you can think of this in terms of
compulsive obsessional disorder or
perhaps even depression you know the
world is an awful place that is true
therefore there's no point in going out
and you know challenging the evidence
that the world isn't an awful place so
I'm just going to stay inside and feel
um
isolated and not move or say very much
um so that would be an example of who
somebody is not very impressionable in
fact their pathology they're misfiring
prevents them from acquiring any
evidence to revise those beliefs so if
you imagine a a species
um that had that same kind of second
order misfiring on this so this is not
the misfiring on the inhibited sword
this is a a failure to infer the second
order statistics the reliability the
Precision
um the variance the entropy of the
content of the things they're trying to
innovate or or make sense so you're
you're left with this notion of a a
species that just cannot respond to
selective pressures for selectability
they can't respond
um by adjusting their evolvability
simply because they're fixed in the in
their way so for the environment on eco
Niche changes in any fundamental way
they're not going to be able to
um to respond to them so I think this
you know there are many examples of this
sort of key
um this key if you like yes I think it
would be called a pathology and in the
sense that in a volatile environment you
would need to optimize the Precision
afforded sensory evidence in order to
make the best sense and understand and
engage with that environment and if you
get that wrong there will be a pathology
um and I think basically Hector's
formulation really drills down and
really focuses on the actual mechanism
of this kind of um this kind of
pathology you know it's all about the
trans-cultural spread of generative
models and and sense making
um in terms of engaging either with
artifacts or indeed with with con
specifics and I repeat it's such a such
an easy thing to get wrong as as events
in Psychiatry you know there are so many
instances of
um
neurodiversity expressed clinically that
I think reflects this this singular
dimension in terms of the ability to get
that balance to get that balance uh
right I remember we discussed last time
again in terms of impressionability and
uh selection for selectability and the
like the same kind of mechanism
unfolding uh your in terms of
evolutionary mechanics but at the level
I think we're talking about today in
terms of
um you know evincing plan pursuing plans
um and novel ways of doing things that
may or may not be recognized uh due to
the due to a failure or not of getting
um being able to suspend the Precision
your prior beliefs I think that that was
essential um central theme I'll just
close
um with an interesting comment that in
terms of the kind of misfiring that um
Hector was implying basically a novel
way of doing things
um being the unique province of those
kinds of creatures that can plan
possibly deeper into the future
um
there's a really interesting sort of
Link back to this Precision notion
in the sense that if you try to simulate
the depth of planning of any sentient
artifact
then the degree to which they are able
to look into the future depends upon the
Precision of their beliefs about the
succession of contingencies what will
happen if if this happens and then what
will happen if that happens so just
technically the Precision of the
transitions amongst worldly states of
Affairs as you roll out into the future
and again you have to estimate that
Precision
um so there's another if you like
point at which Precision gets into the
game but in this instance it's not the
Precision of the cell three evidence but
the prior Precision about the ways
things unfold and what will happen if I
if I do that if you have a low Precision
there then you don't I'm very far into
the future because you lose certainty
and confidence very very quickly after
just a few moves
whereas if you have very precise beliefs
about the
um the state Transitions and the
consequences of various actions or
sequential policies then you can roll
out confidently much further into the
future and perhaps find that Innovative
Innovative solution so again we come
back mechanistically to phenotypes that
have differing degrees of precision
the
um in this instance get into the game in
terms of bounding the
um bounding the the depth of the
planning or the temple Horizons
um that you can entertain when um when
um scoring different plans in order to
actually select the best action at the
moment so for me that Insight is really
useful because I can see how one might
want you know how one could simulate
that quite easy easily in sort of topic
situations so that was that those are my
thoughts inspired by by
Hector's excellent uh presentation
thank you Carl
Dean what say you
well if it's if it's okay I'd like to
sort of step back for a second and
um
because we were privileged to be able to
look at the two papers
almost simultaneously I know
chronologically we've we've split it up
into weeks but
as readers we were able to kind of look
at both papers Side by each I kind of
want to take a bit of a hofstetter
strange Loop
two-sided condition Mobius we've got
that all those representations in our in
a lot of our live stream introductions
so if we were to assume that because
Carl pointed out not everybody can can
accommodate two things at once
perspective if if we can assume that
that doesn't overwhelm my question to
the authors is do they see their own
Journey as a one paper or artifact
artifact morphing into the next
or and as we were pulled out and taken
up by this relationship between
epistemic and pragmatic values when up
taking an active inference perspective
that's part one of the question part two
is the former
is kind of a sequential mechanical
technical side of things the latter is
the combinatorial plus meaning entailed
and entangled so more more where am I
relative
so combined that's a relative depth of
field as setting as establishing
morphing we want to call it that
as active inferences strategy is applied
how do the authors see or potentially
see this perspective combining meaning
the sequential end or the combinatorial
affecting not effecting but affecting
what we believe
because I'm a big I'm a big believer
that we can't just sort of strip the
feelings part of this out I think that's
whether we're talking chimpanzees or
whether we're talking the emotions of
sliding down a snake
those are those are are part of this
thing that we're looking at
I'll just give one short note on that in
the paper sophisticated affect of
inference
they simulated
counterfactual Futures projections about
Futures which are inactive inference
action oriented all Futures are analyzed
and inferred about with respect to
policy selection by the agents and one
of the patterns already appearance in
even the simple simulations were that
even if a very small fraction of
counterfactuals
have like death as an outcome or highly
negative outcomes it can increase the
variance estimator on possible Futures
greatly leading to essentially
ruminative behavior and affective
anxiety around the legitimately
warranted variance in possible outcomes
so I see a key piece of this puzzle to
be entertaining progressively wider time
cones of possible Futures in a
prospective capacity
and entertaining progressively wider
time cones
in the past of causal mechanisms
and somehow negotiating that affect
barometer in the moment as the eye of
the needle
Hector Michael where do you see affect
coming into the snakes and ladders to
copy and not to copy set
um well may I make one or two comments
um first of all in addition to what
Professor Christian has told us about
autism and so on I think it's worth
mentioning uh in the connection of the
question that Daniel has just raised
to say that there is clearly a
difference in the evolution during the
life cycle of
early humans on the one hand and great
apes and probably most human
forerunners on the other
the extinction of the human life cycle
the extension Beyond childhood and in
particular as I mentioned last time
um
the Adolescent growth spurt which we
have but which may not have existed uh
in early homo uh even one and a half
million years ago
I'm sure is relevant to making the
evolutionary uh
step between let us say
the
surprise that perhaps a chimpanzee has
if she
observes a dead bird and then regards as
counter-intuitive because Birds ought
not to be lying on the ground
throws it up into the air but this is a
an individual
spontaneous reaction which is not
um handed on as part of a behavioral
repertoire almost the species
and on the other hand when we begin to
see
the reproduction of
as it were counter-intuitive uh
behavioral sequences such as taking a
lot of flakes repetitively by hand from
a piece of stone using another Stone to
produce an almond-shaped hand ax a
fairly regularly flicked on both sides
something which is not found before homo
appears in the archaeological and paleo
antibiotical record
but which is not something that seems to
be a regular part of human behavior it
is almost as if uh the individual who
made that uh was doing it as a kind of
spontaneous thought of what might happen
uh if I was to do this uh part of the
deep generation of the uh hierarchically
mechanistic mind which Professor fiston
has told us about
a deep generation that however
may have been a misfiring it may have
been simply a personal uh spontaneous
event which is not easily
recognized by others particularly if
they're uh
shall we say to put it mildly their
mental
development is stunted due to the early
adults what is the lack of any
adolescence adolescents in particular
which and uh of course um the
development of the neuronal architecture
of the brain which in modern people
continuous until our mid-20s if this was
not to have occurred uh
as it does not of course in
um even in great apes
then there would have been perhaps
a problem here about the Deep generative
potential of an individual ever being uh
recognized such that
um it isn't just what might happen if I
was to do this with a piece of stone but
what might happen if I was to copy what
that other individual is doing with a
piece of stone
um and this I think is the stumbling
block this is what has uh led to the
snakes and ladders picture it says what
I think has led to
they're very slow adaptation
of technological uh cumulative
technological
um uh handing down from between
Generations or between individuals of
the generation and between generations
and it may well have been the case that
it was not until then uh demographical
as well of course as
biologic paleobiological changes had
evolved in the Guinness hormonal that
there was sufficient intercourse
not very sexual but social such that
um these questions continue to be uh
asked and more frequently and with the
appearance of better and have a more
fluent communication would allow
what we know uh regard as human culture
specifically uh human nature which uh I
think differentiate has differentiated
us ever more from the the great apes I
just
those are my thoughts on the matter
um
thank you Michael
Coral or anyone else please
but I um this
um speak to the question about affect
and what Michael has just treated us too
um
so one way of um conceiving of affect
and Valence and um you know the
emotional aspects of
choosing different plans or making sense
of my own Body Sensations
um is to think about it in terms of
precision estimation
um so one way of carving
um
one way of a very generic way of
thinking about sort of negatively
effectively charged states of mind would
be those states of Mind in which there
is irreducible or unresolvable
uncertainty so you know to put simply
um to be uncertain about what is going
to happen to me or what I should do is
to be in a state of angst and that can
be um
linked to Notions such as anxiety
um and you know with some extra nuances
other
um feelings such as your
um a low affect native that is pervasive
a low mood or or depression
um but I think the key thing here and
indeed many people uh have developed a
calculus of emotion based upon whether
your average level of uncertainty is
increasing or decreasing or is high and
low and adding these things together to
get a an ontology of emotional states or
a purely sort of inference perspective
they're another body of thought and
um literature which links emotions to
um the literary gut feelings
interception
um so that certain emotional states are
just hypotheses about the way that I am
feeling
um now that best explain the Myriad of X
receptive interceptive Sensations so I
think there is a mechanics of affect in
um certainly interceptive inference and
possibly more generally in terms of
active inference
however there is another aspect of
things that we the the feelings that we
might associate when we feel
um compelled to do things and I'm
thinking here not about the irreducible
um or irresolvable uncertainty but about
uncertainty that can be resolved I'm
thinking here when Hector mentioned
um Andy Clark's treatment of surprise
there is also the truism that we expect
to be surprised
um and
technically that lends that can be
explained in terms of
the imperatives for choosing those
actions that will resolve uncertainty
um about the way the world works so this
is just an expression of novelty so if
we anticipate if we if we anticipate
that we are going to be surprised by
some outcome what we are saying is that
that outcome is going to be informative
and that it will reduce some uncertainty
technically it has a high expected
Information Gain so I'm speaking here as
a statistician
and using terms that would underlie the
Bayesian principles of optimal
experimental design that we we do these
experiments uh specifically in order to
get surprising outcomes that are by
definition going to resolve my
uncertainty about my different
hypotheses so if we think about the
um the misfires that are Innovations
these are effectively by definition
novel behaviors
and they are
um the fact that people
um or certain people and certain
creatures engage in
um novel um in novelty seeking is
entirely sensible from the point of view
of the free energy principle because
novelty
um seeking just is an expression of
curiosity it is just an expression of
choosing those outcomes that are going
to yield Rich information that has
um technically a high self-information
or an expected information game so
this is another view of the um if you
like the effective aspect that we do we
are compelled and expect ourselves and
we'll possibly explain ourselves as
being excited
um in a positive way and the opportunity
to resolve uncertainty because we've
seen opportunity to do something novel
what is behind that door you know what
is inside this present you know what
would happen if I did that and that's an
entirely natural
um and bi-natural I mean something that
is easily naturalized under the physics
of self-organization of any system
that has or entails an implicit
generative model of the consequences of
it of its own action so I thought it was
a lovely link between that kind of
um
affect written into the
um the the imperative to seek novelty to
seek surprises in the future
um and what Michael was saying about uh
well yes in order to do that you still
have you still have you have to suspend
your
um your prior convictions because if you
a priori think you know everything there
is no novelty there is no imperative for
exploration uh and you'll just do the
same thing time and time again but if
you're in a if you can recognize that
there is reducible uncertainty and
um
choose those actions that have the
greatest expected Information Gain then
you will necessarily succumb to
um novelty seeking behavior and thereby
discover those misfire Innovations so uh
and it may be that you know there is
um well the story that Michael was
telling was that we are built to be
curious creatures for much longer we are
built to you know to be able to respond
to novelty and to find those Innovative
novel ways of Behaving and uh
um you know so that we remain
um we will We retain that childlike
curiosity
um as part of our IP genetic epigenetic
neurodevelopmental programming for much
longer than other species so I I think
that sort of matches very nicely with
the the sort of the basic thesis that
Hector was proposing during the
presentation it all comes back to
getting the Precision of your prior
beliefs right and suspending
um very precise prior beliefs in order
to explore hypotheses and that
exploration just is in terms of engaging
in novel Innovative behaviors that will
um that you know will resolve your
uncertainty
so I I if that's right the sort of
engenders the question why is there an
evolutionary pressure
for this kind of Eternal childhood so
um I want to ask Michael and Hector
because Michael certainly brought in um
Language and Cultural Niche construction
I I
my guess would be that there will be a
circular causality
um between
um the uh the um
the cultural econish and the phenotypes
the time to adapt to that cultural Eco
Niche such that they are required or the
the phenotypes that have the greatest
adaptive Fitness are those that retain a
greater curiosity
um in the context of the culture in
which they find themselves and part of
that will be necessary to actually
understand the communication and the
signs and the semiotics afforded by
their con specifics which could be read
just as language so my question is did
this Innovative does innovative tool use
does it emerge at um
um stochastically or um you know um at
certain points along with communication
and language
um or
um are they or are they not correlated
and if they are correlated in terms of
you know your historic quickly and what
are their thinkings about the direction
of causative does the fact that you
um remain curious and Innovative for
much longer
um lead to language that we can you know
engage in novel communicative behaviors
or is it that we need to
um remain curious and open-minded in
terms of
um thinking about or entertaining novel
plans and Innovative plans simply
because we have to make sense of a world
that is rich in information because
there is language that is that has been
culturally inherited or is it both as a
is a both top-down and bottom-up
causation
so so two questions language
tool use and copying and the um the
coupling between the sort of
evolutionary and phylogenetic
um so the firegenic on the
um the um sort of phenotypic levels when
it comes to things like language
well
um I wonder if I could come in here
uh Daniel is it okay if I address uh
Carl's questions yes in whatever order
you like
thank you um
but in the first place
there is a voluminous literature on the
relationship between language and the
origins of tool making and Tool use
uh really and there's a lot of
unresolved arguments about whether the
two came together very early in human
evolution let's say between one million
and yeah two million and one and a half
million years ago
as I originally thought some years ago
or whether in fact
languages we know it
or shall we say fluent communication at
least only developed much later as I'm
coming out to believe now and as nowam
Johnson have said for many many years
uh I don't want to get involved in that
because really we would need two or
three programs and a lot of literature
to compare and contrast
yeah
rather I would
query whether we have
an eternal childhood
on the contrary I think that
physiological childhood
is slowed down and when the
Adolescent growth spurt arises after
about the age of let's say nine years
old
but sometimes or perhaps somewhat later
at others
is when we see a major change in
Behavior which is no longer childish but
it's neither is it uh adult
of course we need to go into that we all
know that adolescence can be very
impetuous
um but they can also be extremely
anxious but this brings us to The Angst
that Carl has mentioned and which I
certainly felt uh as and Adolescent
facing the weekly Bible voucher
examinations in human anatomy in the
dissecting room which in those days we
all had to undergo at least in the
United Kingdom as I can sure call the
members and resource that put me into a
state of extreme nervousness
and has given me a lifelong uh worry
about the
uh lack of accuracy uh let alone
Precision in an anatomical description
and identification uh and a concern
um with the statistical
variability in uh and in human anatomy
or aspects of it and actually in general
not necessarily human and its relation
to uh uh process in other words to
physiology and I feel myself much more
despite having lectured in human anatomy
much more uh aligned to physiology and I
spent some time doing neurophysiological
stuff many many years ago you know at
Oxford and getting her
um then uh in the uh classification this
has to be that way and as we were taught
as medical students always think doctor
about the most obvious rather than the
most obscure but we have to have the
whole range before
and this brings in her
um the whole problem of do we think in
terms of
very uh
right or wrong concrete
facts about stuff in general or do we
think in terms of the statistical range
of variability whether it is in terms of
occurrences let's say related to a
question type distributions or to
continuous variants which can let's say
related to gaussian type distributions
and unfortunately it was only much later
in life as I discovered that in fact uh
modern statistics allows these to
approach us to be compared and
contrasted in a uniform manner I didn't
know that
um 50 years ago alas
which shows my my my ignorance
still I would come back to the whole
business of the growth
um curve of humans this clearly has
altered when we look at chimpanzees and
other great apes
basically they don't have much of
anything approaching our adolescents
they don't have this slowing down of
growth and then a recuper recuperation
of the velocity of both combined with
uh most important not merely anatomical
and physiological changes but also
those of
the mind uh the ability to uh innovate
the ability to have lateral thinking or
the ability
um which I have noticed in some um
young people I've met with and
Asperger's Syndrome to be able to
concentrate
and much great in great detail on
particular matters which are
extraordinarily Arcane such as Sanskrit
literature uh in people that are not of
a South Asian Heritage
whereas uh in dealing with other people
that other colleagues they appear to be
uh shall we say gauche
and this is of course well known however
and it indicates the range of
variability
but it is the
change which we all undergo uh in not
merely physical but also intellectual
ability and inquisitiveness which can
get us into trouble uh when we are in
our adolescence and as young men and
women uh given the
a continual and continuous changes in
our neuronal architecture at least until
our mid-20s these days which I think
distinguishes and has distinguished the
evolution of
um homosexual homo in general and Homo
sapiens in particular but I wouldn't
rule out neanderthals or even Homo
erectus
and which I think has been cumulative
and undoubtedly although we have no idea
undoubtedly
enhanced by increased
excuse me
and ever ever more complicated uh
communicate communication
during the the past probably half a
million and certainly quarter of a
million years
this curiosity what would happen if we
did this what would happen if we did
that but
even so things are not rapidly
grasped
and
we see that in different parts of the
world particularly in modern populations
even as have been long separated from
each other
not everything is developed at the same
rate
but well-known examples are for example
uh the wheel which first appears for men
on the Eurasian steps about 5 000 years
ago and it was used for traction
and then appears quite independently in
pre-columba mesoamerica
um about 2 000 years ago
and was not used even though it would
have been very useful being anything as
simple as a wheelbarrow but simply to
move around in your images
whether they were dolls or toys or Gods
with no idea
and another one taken from the same two
areas of the world uh is the Metallurgy
of copper which appears about
well perhaps over six thousand years ago
in Eurasia and possibly two thousand
years ago independently in the New World
and yet
other things happen too for example
in Australia we find modern people
were making hand axes when these had
long ceased to be made by anybody
outside
Australia some of them may even be
um only a few thousand years old
so
this
appearance and disappearance and
reappearance
is something which has not gone away and
must be related somehow to
our ability to
to this deep generation of our
inquisitiveness our curiosity
and indeed our ability
um to not to see the most obvious thing
around us the desire to see only one
simple solution this which so irritated
me when
my teachers Hindi in the united
department when I was a medical student
believed that there was only one right
answer as to
how many heads this muscle had or which
um uh how many how many vertebrates
there were and this or that part of the
vertical column let alone in the skull
and we know how very valuable these
matters can be
so
there's this tension between the desire
for things to be seen in one light only
uh in a one-dimensional way and uh
natural
inquisitiveness this deep deeply
generated uh desire to say
what would happen if it was like this uh
how is it how has it come to be like
that why is everything different and not
the same
I can't put it any other way with that
I've said quite enough
thank you Michael Dean
thanks Daniel um so again this is for
the authors this is
this has been really helpful to me as
observers because that's that's
highlighted
um very clearly in the papers
I see both papers um
speaking to something that I would
describe as conditions set meaning in
the papers examples limit the game to
the game metaphor at least to this type
where there's a limited number of tiles
and a kind of a clear
continuation until a conclusion or
recognize the limit of the species to
nutcracking
so there there's a there's a real clear
idea and Michael's and Hector are both
spoken to
so what was the what was the growth
limit of the of the brain's capacity Etc
what I'm curious about and I and I don't
know if there's a Michael or Hector or
have a
a real clear answer to this but
I'm wondering what and when
was the
was maybe the range of time that we see
the unlocking or or sort of combatorial
explosion or not
what I guess what I'm asking is is
is there a move that we can clearly see
as being something that differentiates
playing which we know happens in a lot
of species and gaming
because as I said at the end of 53.1 I
wondered if it was going to be game on
and so I'm I'm curious what the authors
think about that is there a difference
between playing and gaming meaning that
there's now an actual introduction of
strategy
in this
um so maybe another way of asking it is
there
a moment when you guys can point to it
and say this was kind of when we saw a
a reducing or maybe a um relaxing of a
of a limit-forward world
I wonder whether in fact this difference
is really quite as great as Dean
suggests and whether it may be have
something to do with the
um
ability in
working memory and other aspects of
memory in
dealing with
or in developing a logical mathematical
ability
to
plan or in planning and in communicating
disability such that
uh the planning is no longer at an on an
individual level but it's participatory
and therefore again in other words
um
and perhaps Hector can answer to this
question but I would suggest that
this developed slowly gradually and uh
by no means in a continual let alone a
continuous manner in homo but not in
earlier uh in a way it did not in
earlier and other hominid species
do we see and this I would ask Hector do
we really see
um as I say well chimpanzees or other
great apes developing
the kind of logical math ability to make
very very simple combinatorial
um
associations between objects or
behavioral activities and
developing this into a communal game
which involves other individuals in the
group because as Hector has remarked on
various occasions and informed me
um when we see things like nutcracking
in small groups of chimpanzees it by no
means is copied by all of them uh let
alone copied
um or emulated by all of them but uh and
by no means even when it is with
faithful accuracy and precision in the
manual operations that are required
so that I would ask a question Hector do
we see these associations being
transformed into games
okay and that's that's a good question
um
I mean what do we know it chimpanzes is
that they have promised to do this
second Urban relationships which is like
hierarchical
um ordering of foreign
classify them attending to the color for
instance teams could do that okay if
only color is involved but I can
classify them by color and shape so this
is another order of hierarchy so I can
pick things that are square and red and
put them together so this ability to
abstract
um
a kind of ordering category so that I
have relationship relations like in
analytical reasoning when I I can focus
on one dimension or in another
simultaneously so I can achieve my focus
from one dimension to another in order
to classify things these I think is
quite human like for instance the
Wisconsin cash working test so I can't
shift from one dimension to another to
classify objects or cards and this is
something that seems good
have more problems to do so they might
classify in a first order the categories
like I put things that have a same color
they could learn to do that uh that
wouldn't be a big problem but I guess it
I have to use two Dimensions together to
classify the options they will have more
problems because this involves
considering more one more than one
dimension simultaneously I'm not sure
about making sense here this is the the
Jonas longer work that he did it with
with kids and that's a remarkable work
that Jonas Langer did and then there
were these people in Rome I was I think
it was 40 at the lab of
um
replicated that with
um which advances uh I think it was
espinosi who replicated it and found
that chimpanzees were more compromised
in order to have this kind of
classificatory relations of relations
so and I think that's a very very
remarkable ability that that uh that we
develop so I don't know if I answered
your question Michael
perhaps that comparison
of two dimensions
color and shape
and then the snakes and ladders overlay
that lets us take the hypotenuse
is that abductive jump
enabled developmentally and
neuro-epigenetically by all these
different features which happen over
much slower time scales
especially considering the actual
millisecond time scale associated with
recognition those other changes are so
much slower but the ability to
move diagonally on the grid
through the rows and the columns
and turn that into movement on a
manifolds
is the ability
looked at from the either row or column
perspective to move in both at once
but by condensing those two Dimensions
into one
there can be new kinds of
cognitive movements
and then applying that cognitivist lens
also evolutionary transitions
even without the complex
cumulative
feedback with the eco-cultural niche
merely in the
abductive moment
and just one other piece I wanted to
return to
is that every variable can have a
Precision estimator or not
in the generative models and active
inference every variable can be fixed
and so the model can just be
persistently surprised with no updating
or one can have any kind of Prior or
hyper prior and so on
and that enables learning and that's
what enables not just estimation of the
mean or the sensor of gravity the
expectation of but also the variance the
whole distribution and then it's
um
by applying that kind of precision on
everything view which as
Michael brought up is exactly what
modern statistics does you can't do
inference with the t-test unless you
have the mean and the variance
won't go into any more details on the
statistics but every variable has the
center of gravity mean estimator and the
variance estimator
and so we talked about Precision on
sensory information the mapping between
observations and hidden State estimates
and then also there's this
action-oriented Precision on how things
will unfold
and
you might be able to update your
Precision on sensory evidence by seeing
something different
but updating your Precision on how
things will unfold
is oriented around taking actions
Daniel you must have some questions I I
can't be the only one floating questions
and having my zone of bound and surprise
on being expanded here
I
I I have um questions I can ask you a
question or Michael or Hector or Carl
please feel free
if you owe me I would like to pick up
with something that Professor please
don't mentioned before uh that was kind
of uh it was interviewing because it is
true that some great artists like
Bangkok and others were very creative
and also I don't know if it's
appropriate to say they were in the
world of psychosis I don't know if it's
appropriate because I don't have any
statistics but I'm thinking if
being Innovative is this again is
misfiling so I would like to separate
two things one is how Innovative you are
and I'm thinking in the econish if you
are well adapted to an environment is
not a good idea that you try different
things all the time because imagine that
you have some place where there are nice
berries you have discovered a safe path
to that place
and if you give to that path you go to
the berries you get there you feed so
that's good for you
imagine you want to try something new so
you are very Innovative and one day you
decide to try another path to the very
shortcut
so you have one risk that you can face
new dangers because this part is new you
don't know what is waiting for you there
the other is you face in that you can
get lost and then you could spend the
energy you need to survive so in a way I
don't think that being Innovative is
good in itself
but we have the risk if we are too
conservative that the environment
changes and if the environment changes
significantly we are not well adopted
because we don't have alternative
behaviors that are adaptive to the new
environment so I guess
with this happens like psychological
trades nobody has extremes so we don't
have people with extreme psychological
personalities I mean we have
Pathologists but the selection has
favored kind of intermediate level so I
guess and Professor fristy knows more
about Psychopathology but I guess it
happened with Innovation that we need
some kind of balance
and
what is including for me is
how humans Escape that balance in terms
of how they managed to be creative and
Innovative at times because we are very
uh
we repeat many routines so but there's
still we can be very creative
and we have selected so we have been
successful enough to our economies and
I'm just thinking in this content
factors idea so I think this might have
played a major role the ability to have
counter factors because perhaps instead
of risking my life every time I innovate
I can rehearse what will happen and as
Professor friston mentioned before if I
have a good Precision I can
imagine things that will unfold
if the genetic model is very deep I can
think ahead many steps and see how I
will fare in the future so I can kind of
rehearse things in my head before I put
them into practice in the real world and
this might help me to
be Innovative but with um
a kind of boundary risk or control risk
I don't know if this makes sense but I
think it must be some kind of balance
between
if I can requesting in my account I'm
very good and predicting things that I
will um
evolve or unfold many steps ahead
I can see how I will feel and then I can
risk to be Innovative I don't know I
mean I'm very I'm being very speculative
here okay so I just want to make clear
that I'm being very speculative
please Carl
no no I'd like to speak to that yeah I
don't yes you may be uh speculating uh
but I think those um those observations
are very veridical and very and very
useful
um I mean you've brought a number of
fundamental issues to the table first of
all the importance of being able to plan
um to have a generative model in the
consequences of actions is not the gift
of all species and and in some instances
um in your words when the environment
doesn't change you that would be an
undue complexity cost to carry around a
brain with a generative model or the
consequences of my actions if I don't
need it if I was a virus or an insect I
wouldn't I wouldn't need that it would
be
um it would be very inefficient and so
that sort of lends
um or brings you to a picture
that our world is sufficiently complex
and changing at PACE the
um committing to
um very simple underly expressive
genitive models is not an option and one
really important way of making them more
expressive is to increase that temporal
horizon or temporal depth so that we can
you know in accord with things like
simulation Theory run out into the
future and and now
um become the kind of phenotypes that
can select among a number of plausible
policies
um and you know I think that would be
one bright line between lots of you know
different genres and different species
you know that could be just
um drawn on a dimension which is just
the depth of planning that my generative
model will support
um and we've talked previously about
that being constrained by the Precision
afforded
in a given context
um my beliefs about how I would rely
before into the future so I think that's
just you know from the from my
perspective at least that's a really
important observation that
um the depth of planning is a very
important functional characteristic of
the generative models that are implicit
in phenotypic behavior and possibly in
terms of
um what um what kinds of models are
subject to selective pressure at an
evolutionary or indeed at the oniva diva
Uma Divo level
um the other the other I think key
Insight that you um
you bring to the table here
um relates to
um what affords the right balance
between novelty seeking exploratory
behavior
um and the risks that that would entail
and I think you know
um that from a purely um sort of
mathematical point of view isn't really
important observation
um just to sort of join the dots with
other ways of understanding How the
Universe Works
um that um particular question
um is very usely framed in terms of
constraints so the free energy principle
that from which active inference
inherits is
um one way of or is dual to something
called the maximum entropy principle
under constrain so this was
um brought to physics in the 20th
century by
um a foundational thinker E.T James who
basically rewrote physics in terms of
probability Theory and said that
basically everything that the um of
interest at least or physically
um
conforms to a constrained maximum
entropy principle so that actually is
just a an expression
um or for
um
for tens the free energy principle in
the sense that the constraints
um in from the point of view the
pre-entry principle
um are just what is brought to the table
by a generative model
um and
um the entropy um pertains to the
entropy of belief so you've got this um
this dialectic
um simply at the level of the physics of
measurement and inference which means
that I'm always trying to
um explain any measurement
um such that my predictions are as
accurate as possible but at the same
time
um leaving Having the maximum latitude
so that I don't over commit in accord
with Occam's principle so mathematically
what that means is the entropy of my
beliefs has to be as big as possible
provided I provide provided I have an
accurate um the con given the constraint
that my account or my measurement has to
be an accurate measurement
so that that may sound if you like
completely unconnected to whether I
choose to
um wander away from the berry path and
but in fact exactly the same maths
applies to these quantities either the
constrained entropy or the variational
free energy in the future and what
happens is
um you get exactly the same dialectic
you have two pressures on one hand
um to comply with the Occam's um
principle or Occam's razor and on the
other hand to um
um to you to uh keep all your options
open
um which in a sense is exactly do I uh
comply with the constraints
um
um but I know I'm going to get my
barriers and I'm not going to be eating
my but myself by a predator or do I keep
my options open and try that other path
so this the this sort of dialectic is
just bait into the physics of any
self-organizing system
um and practically
um you know it emerges in a number of
ways one way of writing down the three
energy or the constrained entropy from
James's point of view expected given a
particular policy do I go down this path
or that path is in terms of ambiguity
and risk to you're using exactly your
words you know so the risk is just the
relative entropy on the Divergence or
discrepancy between what I think will
happen and what I expect to happen to me
so I expect not to be eaten and that's
the key constraint at hand here so it's
not about rewards anymore we're throwing
away the notion of rewards and we're now
replacing it with a multi-dimensional
construct which is all the constraints
in the ways of being like having a
certain temperature or not being very
cold or very hot not being eaten not
being dead just keeping within my
characteristic States so you write down
those characteristic States in terms of
constraints and those constraints
basically preclude certain states of
being and then I just compare what will
my States be if I do this and how far
away from
um how far away is that anticipation
from my prior constraints and that and
that literally is called risk it's it's
the Chao Divergence between your policy
dependent
um predictive posterior and your prior
preferences that have the constraints
the other thing is the ambiguity
um and that simply reduces to um making
sure that you make
in a way that um
underwrites a um an unambiguous precise
mapping uh between
um what you see and
um what caused your sensation so you
avoid dark rooms basically you avoid the
dark you avoid dark allies you you don't
go uh where you can't see what's
happening so that's the ambiguity so
together the expected free energy is
equal to risk plus ambiguity
um and
um when read like that then the balance
between the risk and the ambiguity or
another way of carving this up is in
terms of expected information again and
expected cost or
um it's complement expected value where
the value is just the uh how to what
degree am I complying with my
constraints
um is um enables you to to now
write down the balance that resolves to
a certain extent dissolves that
dialectic by the Precision of your prior
preferences your constraints so if
you're the kind of creature or child or
insect
um that has very precise beliefs about
the kinds of outcomes I expect to
anticipate and I may have very precise
beliefs about my body temperature for
example but I may have very less precise
beliefs about where I am in terms of
latitude I could be in Alabama I could
be in Newcastle London I can still be me
but I can't be minus uh your minus two
degrees centigrade and still be me so
some constraints are very precisely
specified and other constraints are less
precisely specified so the risk um is
you know
um is a is determined by
um the Precision of your prior beliefs
about your characteristic States the
Precision of the construct trades you
bring to the table as a phenotype and
some people will be innate and a
completely subpersonal just wide into
your homeostasis and some will be
learnable some may even be
um sort of propositional you know we can
talk about them
um but whatever they have to be there
because they define basically what kind
of thing you think you are and how you
act act accordingly so the balance
between the um
you know whether to go down another path
as opposed to the berry path is going to
depend upon this particular creature of
phenotype and specifically the Precision
of their prior preferences
um in terms of what outcomes they would
uh a priori
um entertain and if they have very very
precise
um preferences over not being eaten and
there's even a marginal small
probability of being eaten if they stray
from the current path then they won't
explore
if on the other hand they have a
slightly more liberal expectation
um about
um being about the encounters with the
predator for example
um then that there will be more
um there will be more
likely to engage in novelty seeking and
exploratory Behavior so you know perhaps
put this even more simply you know this
is the exploration exploitation dilemma
writ in terms of the physics of
self-organization under planning
um and you know and it all reduces again
to precision and in this instance it's
the Precision of the constraints that um
articulated as the uh your prior
preferences your characteristic States
your
um the kinds of states that you you know
you are you believe characterize you
that if you stray from you cease to be
you cease to exist basically
so I thought I was I thought you know
that's I don't think what you said was
speculation I think they're all
fundaments of behavior and actually
um from an ethological uh perspective
you know they speak to the heart of the
of choice behavior
um and you know why we do the things we
do
um and why it is always in the
background the game of saying do I
explore or do I play it safe
awesome thank you Carl Dean
thank you muted Daniel oh thank you
thank you Carl go ahead Dean
I I just like to run with what Carl was
saying
this is mostly for Hector and Michael
um
here's a here's a here's a case in point
all the collective wisdom on the side of
volcano can suddenly be arrested and yet
there is still a Pompeii today
I wonder what your gentlemen think that
says about certain species zone of
bounded surprise
Dean does this refer to the material the
fixed materiality alone
of the ruins of Pompeii of which no more
will ever exist
in the
archaeological context being able to be
unpacked into this Collective wisdom
I'm just curious because we are talking
about regular irregularities and regular
irregularities these these seismic
events occur in the timeline
and I'm just curious what we think then
as we reflect on that and still adopt
that kind of risk mindset as I said I
would just want to run with what Carl
was
was suggesting I I don't know that I
don't know that there's an equivalent
I don't know if if
chimpanzees
would do what humans have done
like see the evidence and still
you know Park themselves right in the
path of of danger I'm just curious what
they think about that in terms of the
the timeline aspect of this
Hector
or Michael go ahead
I think you're muted now Hector
sorry my Microsoft
um
so it's a kind of difficult question and
then I'm not sure if I understood
correctly
um but as you referring to the tone of
Bandit surprisal and linking what what
Professor prison said before
even to take any road which is I don't
know what awaits for me there okay
but if I'm very good
and making guesses or inferring what
might happen based on information I have
gathered before so I'm good at
anticipating what might unfold okay
because I have this complex Machinery
let's call it working memory which is a
construct I have a powerful working
memory for I can't entertain many
possibilities
and there is something that
kind of
ringed a bell when
Professor Freedom was talking of
precision which is the concept of
metacognition
so metacognition refers to thinking
about my own thinking right so I and you
have to clear
um to clear aspects one is how sure am I
about my knowledge for instance
I'm sure I know
something even when I cannot remember
this is the tip of the tongue effect so
I can be or I can give you an answer and
be 100 sure this dance is correct I can
be 80 percent sure 50 sure so I can
evaluate how much sure I am about
something okay so this I think it rings
a bit like precision
so if I make some expect plans and I
think one might unfold I can be very
sure this will happen or not and this
probably has to do with my metacognition
so you have sure I am about what will
happen
and that might help me to decide whether
I go or not
um
and coming back to your son up on the
surpluser I'm not sure if I'm digressing
but
perhaps I can preempt this surprise
if I have a good position a good
metacognition so
if I'm sure that I can reverse things in
my head and see how they will unfold
they won't be that surprising later so I
I'm just speculating perhaps this
ability to have control factors to have
this kind of requesting in my head and
this depth of generative models can
preempty surprise
and here I'm speculating clearly so I
don't know if I'll answer your question
about Pompeii because I'm not sure they
understood but just bring some some
ideas that might be useful but again
they are speculative
it'd be nice just to link that notion of
metacognition and having
um beliefs about beliefs you know the
Precision of a belief about a likelihood
of being eaten by a predator
um but I think that's what Daniel was
speaking to before when he was talking
about
um the hierarchical depth of models of
their increasing complexification and
one really important way of making
making a model of uh more expressive and
context sensitive is to induce a
hierarchy of exactly the sort that
Hector was talking about in terms of the
sort of metacognitive aspect but not
just
um content but crucially again coming
back to the
um the confidence and the uh and the
Precision
um I think that's a really Central
concept but I was just thinking you know
if you had to
commit to what kinds of epigenetically
specified constraints
you would associate with the genome
what in what space would they would they
would they live
um and my guess is that most of it is
about the constraints and within that
it's going to be the constraints on the
precisions that there are certain sort
of innate ranges
um of outcomes that I will entertain
um and
in in principle at least you can
actually just write down an entire
generative model in terms of of
constraints and in terms of precisions
in the sense that
um if the generative model is
universally expressive and everything
goes then you can sort of carve out an
apt uh structural form that um for that
generative model despite shrinking some
of or 99.9 of this overly expressive
generative model to zero with very very
precise constraints so
um well perhaps I'll turn this into a
question you know if if you were trying
to simulate
um artificial life in its most generic
sense if you try to simulate tools for
example the emergency tool use in a
synthetic population
um and you had to actually write down
what could be asked by a genetically or
epigenetically to each subsequent
generation what what kinds of things
would you specify
that's kind of my question in the same
in the same sense how do we
where where do we draw those arbitrary
lines I mean it's this it's the thing
that comes up again and again as we
continue to sort of see the next the
next sedimentary layer of papers
discussing this right but but the fact
that it can be moving and the fact that
it it it isn't con there is a rate
constant that you mentioned in the last
live stream that has to be
um working functioning and effective
and then there's still this question of
so
so what is our our uh what are we
attending to and what are we still
available to all at once and how do we
organize that in a way it that it most
closely as you say precisely it that
that's the best way of describing it
what's really going on
and that
that's that seems to me it needs to be a
moving Target
just one
quick speculative mapping as well first
the
um instead of just stacking bricks with
content on content on content
intercalating layers of content
estimation with metacognitive estimation
is what allows the extendability of the
multi-layer predictive processing type
architectures it's actually like the
back and forth or the interplay
between
the content estimators
and the variance estimators that allows
that model to
not just be described in terms of its
center of gravity but also in terms of
its full distribution and then to Carl's
question about what is being passed down
genetically and epigenetically and
thinking about those terms even
generically like in the context of
perhaps source code and a configuration
file or some other mapping of like what
is inscribed from a classical
information genetic perspective
and then what is contextually and more
rapidly transmitted
there's an interesting angle I could see
it this way or potentially the opposite
but there's a shorter term
epigenetic firing rate
and then a slower updating
of
neuromodulatory like
genetic possibilities kind of opening
and closing valves
over a slower time scale
and then of course these are nested
within another one so what is what is
neuromodo this can also itself be a
firing rate in other ways but just
focusing on this direction
the uh
inscribed constraints
are like the width of the aperture
and then the actual flow of the photons
through the lens is an instantaneous
firing rate that's happening way faster
than the aperture can be dilated or not
and so merely the fact that there are
multiple concurrent time scales and the
associated interplay of their rate
constants tells us a lot about
this kind of learning architecture
what we do without understanding is
the action question and related to our
preferences and precisions
however
it seems pretty key
that to alternate estimates about
content with metacognitive type
estimates and to package that set of two
belief distributions mean and variance
to package those also as one so it can
be handled as
a composite one
and just to point out that um learning
rates are the manifestation of that
second order specification that
precision
so your they are the same thing you know
at every at every time scale right so
you could you could articulate the
um the developmental stages for example
the um
Rejuvenation but certainly you know the
the um which changes say in late
adolescent
um as a programmed learning rate for
learnability that can be read at some
level as a Precision because the
precisions are just the rate constants
that link the state to the rate of
change of the state
um and that basically is just a learning
rate of many many different levels so I
think there's a sort of uniform
um way of putting together these
different Notions some useful Notions
here
um
uh from machine learning are um sort of
the notion of learning to infer you know
so I was just thinking about my an
answer to my own question and clearly
you can't write down a generative model
that's going to be able to
um get up and go to school in the
morning uh all you can do is to um
create a self-organizing blob that has
exactly the right learning rates so that
it is has exactly the right learnability
so that it can acquire a generative
model and learn through experience
dependent plasticity that model of its
little lived world and of course that
little live world has been constructed
by other grown-up
um
babies uh so you know we get back to the
circular causality that evolution is
trying to provide you with the right
ability learning rates precisions and
structural constraints on your
generative model but your generative
models
Evolution's point of view you're
actually creating the environment that
has to be learned so there's to my mind
isn't there's you know a very beautiful
circular causality here that you know as
fast as you're learning
um you're actually creating new worlds
in which to learn I guess we're seeing
that in the moment with the advances in
technology and the like
which brings me back to my question
about the sort of the top down bet
versus bottleneck causation about
um you know what is a good model
of this world what is a good phenotype
[Music]
in our
final 15 minutes or so here
how do we
move beyond the 53.2 either to the
authors their directions and excitements
about
the work or
anyone's exhortations or
raising of possibilities for other ways
that can be developed
I wonder if it's worth bearing in mind
that
increasing technological
not necessarily complexity but at least
variability
May well have
permitted a reduction
in selection pressure
on the
phenotype
and evidently affecting
uh
the genotype and epigenetic
uh variability I see this because
I would like to draw attention to the
the graph which I
presented last week
which was taken from Professor Philip
tobiases
work on early humans
showing an increasing
the range of variation
in the cranial capacitor of
bipedal hominids from the
australopithelines through to homo
sapiens
suggesting a reduction
in
um selection pressure or
particular
um well for the size of the brain
basically uh
I find it hard not to relate this
to
the advantages that slowly accrued to
ol use and thereby of course the
variability and variation as to making
um
Rabbi reducing the risk or some of the
risks are existential risks
um
that otherwise
played or have plagued
other homonyms where the excellent
whether the ancestors were excellent
great apes or indeed the earlier forms
of
bipedal or many names or celebrity
science balance therapists Canyon sulcus
Etc
uh well
who knows but it's it's perhaps um
uh not totally irrelevant that this uh
variability
has grown over the past couple of
million years and is now very wide as I
mentioned uh last week
this I think is in contradistinction to
the the way in which
selection pressures have been highly
discriminatory in for example producing
let's say the wide range of Darwin's
famous Galapagos finches yeah just to
give a well-known example
[Music]
thank you Carl
I'll ask um
coming back to this theme of um
selection for selectability
um and the notion of
um
Precision or learning rates cast in
terms of mutation rates so you're my
favorite example of and I'm sure there
are better ones nowadays when I was
reading around this subject my favorite
example was
um the Storyteller by Ernst Mayer about
drosophila fruit flies being reared in
volatile versus non-volatile environment
so you're rearing generation of
generation at a fairly fixed temperature
and then an equivalent uh set of
generations where they vary the
temperature a few degrees plus and minus
and what they showed was that the
mutation rate
of the drosophila in the volatile
changing environment
were greater than the mutation rate the
genetic mutation rate in the less
volatile population or transgenerational
populations which I think was a
beautiful example of selection for
selectability itself that you know that
um increased variation
um certainly or it's you know phenotypic
expression of implicit increased genomic
variability was itself an Adaptive
response to to the rate of change of the
environment so my question is is there a
similar sort of picture or view of
um variation in either phenotypic or
genetic
um characteristics in
um over a longer time scale in in sort
of um human evolution and if there is
is there any evidence
um that there is in the past Century or
so
um
perhaps this is a bit of an ambitious uh
ask but is there any evidence that the
the the there has been a sort of face
transition in the variability and the
evolvability and the associated
um phenotypic variation
the empirical or an empirical
research agenda would be to make a
hierarchical active inference model and
perform Dynamic causal modeling on
different variability characters across
levels of phenotypic and genotypic
integration
and have that model
in use
but a very provocative and interesting
question Carl
and to what extent is it happening with
our cellular architecture
and to what extents
are these processes happening with our
niche
given these unique cumulative cultural
generative model generative process
thinking through other Minds
increasingly the production of artifacts
that enable
not just offloading but Outsourcing
these do represent unique cognitive
niches
and so
it will be quite interesting to
investigate
perhaps if we each want to have some
closing
rounds
thoughts
perhaps Dean with the first word
thank you because you know I hate having
the last one I'm just curious gentlemen
thank you first again for for your
generosity I'm just curious now that
you've dipped your toes in this this
active Insurance Institute live stream
world what are your what are your
impressions is was it was it was it
helpful at all
who is next
so I think it has been very
um useful and mostly very fun I mean
I've enjoyed a lot to have this
discussion with all of you so it's been
very enjoyable
um and just for the future
um
I'm just wondering if there is such a
thing like preempting surprise based on
these counter factors I guess maybe it's
already written and discussed and it's
all clear but I wonder that this might
be an interesting idea to to explore if
I can preemptive surprise
before I act I mean for even acting but
that's kind of
maybe that's resolved already
anyway it has been fun thank you all
honestly
thank you that makes me think about
saying I don't mean to surprise you but
that's actually going to increase it's
like oh boy has someone been injured
but what is the show not tell
of preempting surprise
so that with a linear string in time
there is the path from the old Berry
Patch to the Newberry patch
such that it appears to be
within a nested hierarchical model the
path of least action to follow
though in a less nested model
it would be quite surprising
Michael
or Carl you're kind of closing thoughts
or questions
as we bring this set of 53 to a close
well I'll let Michael have the last word
um
and uh just speak to you what you just
said in Hector's um comment I I think
there's a lot of interest in that in in
that notion you know sort of trying to
preempt uh surprise I mean a simple
reading of risk minimization you're just
basically not engaging in policies that
are going to result in surprising
outcomes where surprise is just the
violation of Pride preferences
um so at that level I think that's that
that sort of um
almost a truism
um but there is an interesting
um there's an interesting sort of
implication of that which leads to
Notions of
um the way that we choose to behave
epistemically in terms of avoiding
information that would be very
surprising
um sometimes articulate in terms of
optimism bias sometimes in terms of
wishful thinking but the kind of paradox
that you get when we are base Optical
creatures us and yet we don't want to
open the letter from the GP giving us
our most recent cancer results or we
don't want to open that letter by
whether we fail to get that job or pass
that exam or indeed the anatomy
dissection driver there are certain
things that we avoid there are certain
surprises that we avoid let's put
another way there are certain ways of
preempting Surprise by avoiding knowing
stuff that we might find surprising
um and that's that's an emerging
literature now which which takes you a
little bit outside your your comfort
zone but it's a fascinating literature
okay you'll find things like Trends in
cognitive and Science and the like in
answer to to Dean's question about
um these sessions because this is not my
first session so but um I this but this
does exemplify it yeah it's for fun
um we're amongst friends and
indulging ourselves and those people who
care and listen to us so I think the
next thing to do is is the next Horizon
although I do think Dynamic goals are
modeling of
um evolutionary trajectories is an
excellent idea I I suspect the heavy
lifting now is to get the ideas that
we've been talking about out there I
think that's what Michael and Hector
have to do basically is just keep keep
on telling the story and in my
experience usually takes about five to
ten years before people start listening
okay
thank you Carl Michael with the last
word
well there have been these sessions have
been fun and most uh Illuminating
there's a lot to be done on the whole
matter of whether there have been phase
transitions in the evolution of what we
might call evolve ability in the
Guinness homo over the past two million
years there are big arguments amongst
human evolution Specialists between
whether there was a unitary
evolutionary
um
whether a unitary evolutionary model is
acceptable or as uh lump as myself would
like to believe or whether in fact there
was a big
um uh bush with a lot of dead end
separate
unsuccessful
species like homo floresiensis
um
or even perhaps neanderthals uh with
whom I've had a lot of contacts have the
excavated about 15 of them
um
and these arguments are highly relevant
to the matter of
cognitive Evolution and indeed as to
whether uh the record of artifacts and
tools uh can indeed uh inform us that I
believe it can about uh just how
um
and how slowly I would say uh Evolution
proceeds preceded
um
of course the Splitters believe it
happened in in leaps jumps and leaps
um I'm rather convinced darwinist I
believe that things happen very very
slowly and that we have to concentrate
and with this I can conclude uh on
the especially the neural epigenetic
modification of uh genetic expression uh
as uh affecting not merely morphology
and Physiology but also I would say
cognition and uh in the matter in Hand
of course
the ability or not to uh and there's our
surprisals
affect uh onlookers and other people uh
permitting
um let's just say modification of
behavior in a very wide in a far wider
uh with far wider results than those
that occur in many other uh species
um including some of those of our
closest uh our closest planet
relatives and thank you very much for
organizing this session Daniel and Dean
it's been a pleasure to take part
I'm trying to have this terrible uh
appearance but I
I really can't do much about that at the
moment
but well after a few days
thank you all Michael at least you have
an excuse I have no excuses at all
right
till next time long live the mean long
live the variance
thank you
bye everybody